<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Londons new colours displaid: or, The snake in the cities grasse-green petition discovered. For preventing the horrid mischiefs thereby intended, against the army, and all the well-affected people in city and countrey.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E452_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864320</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864320</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116547</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116547)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 72:E452[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Londons new colours displaid: or, The snake in the cities grasse-green petition discovered. For preventing the horrid mischiefs thereby intended, against the army, and all the well-affected people in city and countrey.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 13".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116547:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>LONDONS New Colours diſplaid: OR, The SNAKE in the Cities graſſe-green Petition diſcovered. For preventing the horrid miſchiefs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by intended, againſt the Army, and all the well-affected people in City and Countrey.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Viridi latet Anguis in herba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>NOthing is more evident, then that London hath been long in diſpute, what Colours to hold forth, that ſhould demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, who they were for, and who they were againſt; and loe, now they are reſolved to beare the very ſame with the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants in Kent, the Common-Councell having ſo determined it, the Petition of the one and the other, being both of one and the ſame Colour and frameing.</p>
            <p>But good, honeſt, underſtanding London, <hi>(I</hi> pray thee) wilt thou now ſuffer thy ſelfe to be thus cheated, ſurprized, and abuſed, by a confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy of Malignants crept into thy Common-Councell? Haſt thou ſo many yeares been a maintainer of the Liberties of the people, and that with the ſtrength of thy youth, thy blood and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, againſt all arbitrary power in whomſoever; and wilt thou now be made more inſtrumentall in the thraledome and miſerie of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then any other part of the Nation? Waſt thou firſt in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to oppreſſion; the firſt example and leader towards freedome? Didſt thou burne as a clear light unto others, to goe out thus like a ſtinking ſnuffe thy ſelfe? Oh, farre be it from thee! ſhame not thy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116547:2"/>
judgement and conſcience thus to all Poſterities. Let it not be ſaid, that London was ſo fooliſh, ſo mad, as wilfully to betray it ſelfe and the whole Nation into bondage; and through ignorance and ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſſe to run headlong into thoſe traps and ſnares, which no terror or danger could ever drive them into: nay, to beg, petition and give thanks for being put into the moſt ready way to be made irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſlaves. Open your eyes and ſee, if it be not ſo: and if you find it ſo, conſider what thoſe men deſerve, who have thus abuſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded you.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, ye are made to fawne and proſtitute your thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to the Parliament, <hi>for their many favours, in granting ſever all of your Petitions;</hi> but ſure you are not ſo farre blinded, as not to ſee this palpable juggling. Do you not know, that divers in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Common-Councell are confederates to deceive you, and all that have oppoſed the King throughout the Land? Do you not ſee they are reſolved to do that for him by craft and fraud, that he was never able to do for himſelfe by force? What Petitions did they ever grant you, that were not firſt contrived and plotted by themſelves, and then cunningly laid to be acted in Common-Councells, and ſo to come in State and formall Equipage preſented by your Aldermen and Common-Councell-men, and then be printed with an Anſwer ſutable, to beget repute and credit abroad, and conſequently, the like Petitions, from all parts?</p>
            <p>Juſt thus it was with that great Remonſtrance of your City, which bred the firſt ſcab between you and that worthy Army, which under God preſerved you, your wives, children and eſtates, from that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and ruine lately threatned againſt you <hi>by the King,</hi> (though theſe deceivers would make you forgetfull of it) and which bred you ſo great miſchiefe, that it's wonderfull the ſame deluders ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, you could be ſo ſo one again liable to the ſame deceit.</p>
            <p>Is it poſſible you can forget the late diſmal time you were in, when, by the inſolence and treachery of theſe violent and treacherous men, the Army was inforced to march to London. You cannot but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the many ſcandalous reproaches they then caſt upon them, under what bloodie and ravenous ſhapes they preſented them to you, on purpoſe to engage you into a warre againſt them: And when their orderly and harmeleſſe march through your wealthy City, had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them all to be falſe, how ſuddenly did they turne this their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116547:2"/>
into poiſon, perverting, what they did (meerly to let you know the Army intended not your ſpoile or ruine,) into an Argument of their Pride &amp; Haughtineſſe, as if they had done it in way of triumphing over you, manifeſting that nothing can be in it ſelf ſo innocent &amp; harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, but malice can turn, into the moſt helliſh Conſtruction.</p>
            <p>Then the decay of trade, deerneſſe of food, continuance of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize and all the burthens of the Land, muſt ſtill be laid to the charge of this Army, not that they deſerved ſuch a charge; but becauſe this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my muſt be made odious, before the People would be induced to riſe, or a cleare way be made for the King. And this work is plied all the winter long, girding at, and provoking the Army beyond all patience. Which, (as one evill ever begets another) brings a part of the Army to White-Hall and the Mewes: And oh, with what art this was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcanted upon and heightened! This was ſuch an affront, as was not to be borne. Then after a while comes the tumult, no way to be appeaſed but by the Army, none other regarding it. And the very appeaſing of it, is with all poſſible skill made a crime equall to, nay, ſurmounting the tumult it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Well, in this time motions are made for a reconciliation, the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia is to be changed, the Mayor and Aldermen in the Tower to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed, the 11. Members and others to be reſtored, and the like. And all this and more is done and the Army oppoſes not, nor repines, as being willing to paſſe by as much as is poſſible. But no ſooner is this done, but to the old work againe. And this City, that in moſt dangerous times, could ſend a full relief to Gloceſter, affords no aſſiſtance for ſubduing either the Kentiſh or the Colcheſter malignants, nay, ſuffers <hi>Goring,</hi> that arch Malignant and old Projector, to noſe them at Bow for many daies, without any check or controule from this City. Which yet in theſe mens conceit and reſolution, muſt eat up and devoure the whole Army. But all parties are not yet agreed, neither ever will be, to ſo baſe, ſo ungratefull an end.</p>
            <p>And now in this nick of time, whiles the Army is imployed part into Wales, part into Kent, part into Eſſex, &amp; another part in the North; whiles the Scots and other forreigners are expected, and danger every where threatneth; now, now onely is the time (as theſe men would make you believe,) for you to petition for a perſonall treaty, as the onely meanes to put an end to all theſe differences and diſputes. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſo it would; but how? Not as you expect, but as theſe deceivers
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116547:3"/>
intend: for you and they are not one in this buſineſſe, how faire ſoever they pretend. For you have (even multitudes of you) voluntarily and faithfully expended of your eſtates and ventured your perſons in the late warrs againſt the King. Many of you have ſpoken largely, and ſome of you have bin inſtrumentall in bringing his inſtruments and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents to condign puniſhment. Many of you have ſerved in Committees as aſſeſſors Sequeſtrators or Collectors; With moſt of theſe you will find it otherwiſe. When plots to deſtroy you have been deeply laid and liſts found; they have been far enough out of danger. The ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Major <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lph</hi> (being a health, ye muſt all look to pledge, when it comes to your turnes,) they have (ye ſee) fine contriving wits, and want not ſwearers on theirſide, O Wretches? Moni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s tis confeſt, they have disburſt, but how much to the King more then to the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament (in the time of its integritie) they feare will one day be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, except by a perſonall treaty, they and their friends get above you all.</p>
            <p>Now, that you may not (if poſſible) ſuſpect their pernicious meaning, (knowing that neither Aldermens and Commons-Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens gowns will cover their groſſe hypocriſie) they put on that Cloake of Religion that ſeldome hath failed them in hideing their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits; <hi>makeing very ſowre faces</hi> (in this ſecond page) for <hi>the growth of ſuperſtition, Hereſies, Shiſmes, and Prophaneneſſe,</hi> occaſioned (forſooth as they ſay) <hi>by the long unſettlement of the Churches.</hi> O the growth of Hypocriſie and Preſumption, thus to gloſſe their treacherous and bloody intentions with pretences of Religion!</p>
            <p>But what mean they by the growth of Superſtition, except the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viveing of the Service-Booke, which in their Hearts none love more then moſt of theſe? As for Hereſies and Schiſmes, though moſt of them underſtand not truly what thoſe words meane; yet, 'tis eaſie to diſcover they intend thereby, to make odious all that have cordially oppoſed the King, or ſhew any reſpects to this Army. And as for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, certainly they mean neither <hi>lying,</hi> nor <hi>over-reaching</hi> nor <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving in traffique,</hi> neither <hi>pride,</hi> nor <hi>covetouſneſſe,</hi> nor <hi>abuſing the name of God and Religion to villanous purpoſes;</hi> and you will eaſily believe a perſonall treaty will occaſion neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leſſe ſwearing nor leſſe drinking, nor any fewer of theſe vices, inſomuch as if they are taken, as they ſeem to mean by contraries, they will then appear rather to intend the growth of all theſe, then of the contrary vertues.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116547:3"/>
As for the <hi>unſettlement of the Church,</hi> they uſe this phraſe of ſpeech, as the reſt, even meerely to deceive. For aſſure your ſelves, you intend one thing and they another, except you mean the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of <hi>Epiſcopacis</hi> or <hi>Prelacie,</hi> and of all their ſequeſtred delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Miniſters, whom you know they dote upon and idolize a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove meaſure.</p>
            <p>And for the late <hi>Commotions in ſeverall Counties, which have been faithfull &amp; ſerviceable to the King and Parliament</hi> (I, there's the Snake in this graſſe green,) <hi>King and Parliament.</hi> O that was wiſely remembred! The Parliament to the hearts griefe of theſe his truſty-ſervants, have too long forborne this Oracle-like expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by which ſo many thouſands were in ſnared: wherefore theſe men longing to ſee them at it againe, doe help them to one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall treaty, that it may be ſo for ever, <hi>King and Parliament,</hi> which by the way is an Hyſteron Proteron, the Cart before the Horſe, not thought on.</p>
            <p>Are there Commotions in ſeverall Counties? no mervaile, when both Parliament-men and ſuch grand Cittizens as theſe, foment them. No doubt, the Counties had continued faithfull ſtill, but for theſe faithleſſe ones; and the blood that is ſpilt in them, will at the end be ſeen at theſe mens doores; though now lap-wing like they by their crying and condoleing would put it farre from them And it's hoped thoſe Counties al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eady ſee their errour, and will be wiſer for the time to come, and liſten to more honeſt and wholſome Councels.</p>
            <p>And who will believe, but the revolt of the ſhips is a whelp of the ſame litter. For who have hitherto bin more faithfull to the intereſt of the People and freedome of the Nation, then the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners in generall have bin? And who more rejoyce in their revolt then <hi>theſe men, who are chiefe ſtirrers in this Petition,</hi> and hopeing thereby a neceſſite of compliance in Parliament to their deſires? But how abominably baſe is it to plot theſe things, &amp; then to cry out, that <hi>this threatneth the eminent deſtruction of trade?</hi> O friends! could theſe rich and wealthy. Aldermen and Common-Councell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as ill brooke theſe ſtops and decayes of trade, as moſt of you can, they would not be ſo brisk upon theſe diſaſters, nor ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116547:4"/>
in theſe wicked practiſes. But by this they evidence, that they regard not the good of Mariners nor Cittyzens, but would by all poſſible meanes, though by impoveriſhing and beggering all ſorts of inferiour people, neceſſitate them to promote their wills, by crying out with violence for any thing, as impatient of delay; and rather then faile, to riſe in tumults and uproares, to force theſe wicked mens ends. But it is hoped both ſea-men and Land-men, Cittyzens and Country men, will be warned out of hand, and returne to their firſt love, even the <hi>freedome of the Common wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this grieves them not ſo much, as that it alſo <hi>tends to the utter ruine of King, Parliament and Kingdome.</hi> Here are two Carts before the Horſe. For in true Heraldrie, the Kingdome or People ſhould have bin firſt, as the originall of power, and next the Parliament as repreſenting them, and laſt the King, as being at moſt, but the chiefe officer of the Common wealth, and only <hi>ſingulis major;</hi> But it ſeems this will not diſgeſt with <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O, but all this while, the <hi>King</hi> is in danger of ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine! I pray you friends, enquire how. In whoſe hands is hee? What hath the man done, that any one ſhould thinke him worthy of ruine? Alas, <hi>the King can doe no wrong,</hi> nor hath done any in theſe mens Divinity and Morality too. (Say you) What hath the <hi>Man</hi> done? O blaſphemy! Here's prophaneneſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed! The King a man? He muſt ſurely bee more then a man, that can doe no wrong. But ſo it is, or no credit is to bee given to theſe his deare friends. All the <hi>deferrings, diſſolvings,</hi> and <hi>aboliſhings of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> with all <hi>arbitrary Patents, Ship-money,</hi> and all ſorts of other <hi>Projects</hi> were no crimes in him. All this <hi>long and bloody warre carried on by him is nothing.</hi> All the <hi>Plots againſt this City and Parliament,</hi> nothing. All
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116547:4"/>
theſe late <hi>Commotions and Inſurrections,</hi> nothing? All the <hi>blood of Rochell, Ireland, England and Scotland, ſpilt by his meanes and procurement,</hi> nothing? yea, and in a word, all the <hi>Parliaments heavy accuſations,</hi> of all the <hi>hainous, odious, and bloody crimes againſt him</hi> nothing. and ſo we muſt all ſweare, they are, if not leſſe then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if now after all, nothing can preſerve us nor ſettle the peace of the Nation, but a <hi>Perſonall Treaty with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh, thou just and righteous God, that ſeeſt and knoweſt theſe things, and who in this their Petition art made uſe of frequently to ſerve the wicked ends of theſe men, do thou blast them with the breath of thy mouth, and turne all their Machiavilian ſtratagems upon their owne heads. And we beſeech thee (in ſuch meaſure) to open the eyes and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the understandings of thoſe whom thou haſt authorized with power, that they may not onely ſee and conſider, that thou judgeſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgement without reſpect of perſons, and bindest Kings in chains, and Nobles in fetters of iron, but that they may learne alſo to judge rightly without reſpect of perſons, and reward every man according to his works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You all heare, (friends) how things go in Scotland, that they have had a Malignant Parliament, endeavouring might and maine to raiſe forces and bring an Army into England. To doe what? why <hi>to eſtabliſh Religion, and for defence of the Kings honour and greatneſſe according to the Covenant,</hi> juſt in the very language of theſe Petitioners; and eſpecially <hi>for a perſonall Treaty with his Majeſty.</hi> 'Tis marvell the word <hi>Sacred</hi> is not added by them or our Aldermen. But it ſeems that's forborne, till his Majeſty have left ſwearing at every other word, or till after the perſonall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and then the King ſhall have all his greatneſſe, honour and prerogative againe.</p>
            <p>But ſure the Parliament of Scotland is not malignant. They are abuſed and injured. It's not poſſible, after all their ſtrivings and oppoſition to the King, that thoſe people ſhould be ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh as to chooſe a malignant Parliament. Yet, ſo it is, the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of well-meaning people hath been ſuch, that for feare of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116547:5"/>
chooſing ſuch as favour Sectaries (by whom they as well as we have been preſerved) they have choſen abſolute Cavaliers and Malignants, ſworne vaſſalls to the luſts of the King, ſuch as hope to be ſharers in the ſpoile of his future Tyranny, and to be petty-Tyrants under him themſelves, which is the great intereſt of all the degenerate Gallants, that formerly have or doe at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent warre againſt the Common-wealth on his behalfe: This the honeſt party have perceived too late, to their griefe.</p>
            <p>For already, they begin to impriſon the beſt-affected and moſt zealous Miniſters and others; and it is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they have executed ſome of the Miniſters. But ſure they are not as yet ſo impudently baſe, though it bee much to be feared, they will doe it, if timely help ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare not here; which muſt be, even by your diſclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and renouncing theſe wicked men, and this their accurſed Malignant Petition, which is a thouſand times worſe then that which was called the Pluſh Petition, and would have been ſo taken, but that ſome of you who (otherwiſe are godly minded) are ſeduced to appeare therein. Nay, if both Lords and Commons were now, as in the time of that Petition they were affected, in ſtead of thanks, they would have ſhewed them their errour, and how contrary ſuch a Petition is to the freedome of the Nation.</p>
            <p>But it is evident, they are now Confederates with theſe men, and intend <hi>under the cunning plot of a perſonall Treaty,</hi> fairely and handſomely to ſeale and deliver up to the King, not onely the juſt Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Liberties of the people, with Excize, and all their oppreſſions to boot unreckoned for, and unpuniſhed: but alſo the lives and eſtates of you, and all that have cordially oppoſed him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:116547:5"/>
And for this end it is, theſe falſe Common Councellmen, and Aldermen (who to diſtinguiſh them from you, ſhall henceforth be called Common-Hall men, for that you know is their right title) for this end (I ſay) did theſe Common-Hall men ſo earneſtly petition for a perſonall Treaty, and continuance of the brotherly union between the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> Their meaning is, between the Malignants Parliaments in both, <hi>According to the Covenant,</hi> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that was well remembred, that covers and colours all Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy. O this <hi>Covenant</hi> of ours, ſerves for many good purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. For we can neither preſerve our Enemies in our own boſomes, divide amongſt our ſelves, nor find quarrell enough to deſtroy our friends, without the help of this Covenant. Which though many of us have taken in the ſincerity of our hearts, yet we ſee it is now made uſe of, to all ſorts of ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, cloſe and treacherous deſignes.</p>
            <p>And what is there now wanting, but that by the <hi>happy union</hi> (of the Malignants in both Nations) <hi>between the King: Majeſty, and the Honourable Houſes of Parliament,</hi> all whom they call Round-heads in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſhall very ſpeedily be deſtroyed, <hi>even with as good a riddance as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in Ireland were, by His Majeſties good catholick Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects there,</hi> who may hereafter be invited to compleat this happy union? Yes, this is yet wanting: the Committee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, muſt firſt agree at what place and time this perſonall Treaty muſt bee. Then the <hi>King</hi> muſt be demanded out of the hands of the Army. This they ſuppoſe, will be ſom what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, as tending to the ruine of the Army, of all the honeſt party in <hi>England,</hi> and of the cauſe for which ſo great floods of blood hath been ſpilt, and oceans of treaſure ſpent, and being no leſſe in effect, then to give up their Swords into the hands of their perfidious vanquiſhed enemies. But here is the plot; if the King be denyed, then preſently flies out Declaration upon Declaration, againſt all the Officers and Souldiers of this rebellious and diſobedient Army, declaring them once more traitors and Rebels in the higheſt degree; denouncing death and ſequeſtration, to all that ſhall any wayes aſſiſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116547:6"/>
them with Men, Horſe, Money, or Plate, in theſe their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous and rebellious practices, tending to the diſſolution of all Government, and the u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter ruine and decay of Trade; (for it muſt be in the Kings old tearmes.) And then up goes another Army under <hi>Major Generall Brown,</hi> the <hi>Presbyterian Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tier,</hi> whom t'is thought <hi>you that are honeſt</hi> will ſo farre favour, as to aſſiſt in raiſing of thoſe new forces, <hi>which if you do,</hi> then they are paſt doubt of carrying on their work againſt the Sectaries, <hi>(according to the Covenant)</hi> not ſeeming to be againſt you, but rather for you, till they have got you all within their clutches, and caught you it this Trapp. For if you that are godly countenance not their work, all is loſt; the Trained bands and Auxiliaries will not then go out, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all endeavours and Devices to engage their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, the Countries will not be deluded not come in to any purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But be you ſure, to keepe <hi>Scotlands</hi> proceedings in your eye, and look no other way. Think upon their impriſoning of godly men already, and adhere no longer to theſe wicked diſſembling <hi>Common-Hall men,</hi> but ſeparate your ſelves from amongſt them; do not you aſſiſt theſe workers of iniquity, &amp; you ſhall ſee them confounded. But if you give them the leaſt countenance, you will find ſuch a confluence of mad and rude people inſtantly flock to them; that, though they are never ſikely to prevaile againſt the <hi>Army</hi> and their friends, yet ſo great may be the diſturbance, that your <hi>City</hi> will be much indangered, your wives and Families affrighred, and what will then become of <hi>Trading?</hi> Certainly this is not the way to a ſpeedy end, (except by your deſtructions) but to the leng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of your diſtractions. For it cannot be immagined, that the Army and honeſt party throughout the Land, will be ſo eaſily vanquiſhed, as theſe hot-ſpirited men conjecture. It will coſt hot water, before that be done. They have not yet ſhewed themſelves either <hi>Fooles</hi> or <hi>Cowheards,</hi> neither hath the providence of God been wanting, to further their juſt and honeſt undertakings. And if theſe new ſtirrers had either <hi>Wiſdom, Grace,</hi> or <hi>Thankfulneſſe</hi> in them, they would
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116547:6"/>
conſider their <hi>lenity</hi> and <hi>unbloody</hi> diſpoſition when they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, and not provoke them into a worſe and more violent temper.</p>
            <p>But what meane the Petitioners, by grounding their hopes upon ſeverall expreſſions of his <hi>Majeſty and both Houſes of Parliament, in their ſeverall and reſpective Declarations?</hi> A Declaration there was indeed lately of the Parliaments, <hi>ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth divers high crimes and offences of the</hi> King, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to make <hi>no further addreſſes to him, but to ſettle the Kingdom without him.</hi> There was alſo ſome time ſince ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Declaration that told him, it was not ſafe for him to come to the City or Parliament, untill he had given ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for all the <hi>innocent blood</hi> that had been ſpilt.</p>
            <p>Had our <hi>Common-Hall men</hi> (think you) theſe Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of both Houſes in mind, when they framed this Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? The <hi>King</hi> alſo hath ſet forth ſo many Declarations of his love to this City, that its hard to judge which they mean. As when this City was in moſt ſtraights, and he in greateſt hopes and power, he declares it death for any to hold Trade with the City, or to bring any kind of proviſion to it. And he gives them another ſecret token of his Kingdnes at the ſame time, in the Plot of <hi>Tomkins</hi> and <hi>Challoner,</hi> and declares the Parliament to be no true, but a counterfect Parliament, and ſets up another at <hi>Oxford,</hi> by <hi>Declaration</hi> too. And now of late came out a <hi>Declaration</hi> of his, of the <hi>old ſtampe</hi> in high <hi>prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative</hi> termes, as high as <hi>Kent</hi> or theſe <hi>Common-Hall men</hi> could wiſh or deſire. Be like <hi>Osburn</hi> was then at work, and this language of the <hi>Kings</hi> was coined for the head of an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> what Declarations they mean, they have not expreſt, and till they do, it will be good for every <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> man to be mindfull of theſe, and to conſider whether the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opard be yet without his ſpots, or the Black-more have changed his skinn,</hi> and by wiſdom to prevent the great miſchiefe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; And be not now, after ſo many years experience, like young birds, to be caught with ſo palpable chaffe as this.</p>
            <p>But this, may you &amp; <hi>Scotland</hi> ſee, comes of <hi>warming Snakes</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116547:7"/>
               <hi>in your boſomes;</hi> no ſooner get they heate, but they ſwell with <hi>venim, and threaten your deſtruction.</hi> Who would have thought the late <hi>exiled Members,</hi> and the late <hi>impriſoned Major and Aldermen</hi> would ſo ſo one have returned to their <hi>old Vomit,</hi> and ſo greedily, <hi>lick up the filth of their former Remonſtrance?</hi> O ſhame! O ignorance! O ingratitude and ſottiſhneſſe<hi>!</hi> why, what do they immagine? can they think, that all the wel-affected in <hi>England</hi> will not gather themſelves together from all places and corners of the Land, and unite with the Army, rather then to be over run &amp; over reacht thus? What? to be <hi>petitioned</hi> out of their lives, liberties, Eſtates; to be <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted</hi> into bondage! No, may he be <hi>beared</hi> through the <hi>eares,</hi> nay through the <hi>noſe,</hi> and burn'd in the <hi>forehead for a vagabond,</hi> that wil not come forth to help the Lord againſt the mighty. Yea, curſe them bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>terly that comes not forth now to help the Lord againſt theſe, who are ſo mighty in their deceit, and bloody in their intentions.</p>
            <p>See, but where theſe men would have this perſonall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <hi>in the City of London.</hi> That's their deſire, though the words following ſhew they are aſhamed to ſpeak it abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and therefore add, <hi>or in ſome other convenient place;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for raiſing of Tumults, elſe what ailes the Iſle of <hi>Wyght?</hi> No, but where it may be moſt for the <hi>honour and ſaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty of his Majeſties Royall Perſon.</hi> What could <hi>Goring</hi> have ſaid more like a flattering Courtier?</p>
            <p>And unto this perſonall Treaty, they humbly deſire, that the it brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> (that is the Malignants, eſpecially Duke <hi>Hamilton)</hi> may be invited, that ſo according, to <hi>the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Aliegiance, Proteſtation, ſolemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, his Majeſties Royall Perſon, Honour, Greatneſs and Eſtate may be preſerved,</hi> even to the uſe and benefit of the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, that ſo they may be inabled to revenge themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates of the Roundheads and Sectaries,</hi> and all peaceable people under theſe titles; and at beſt, bring them to ſequeſtrations and compoſitions; to hang up the <hi>Miniſters</hi> (after their brethren of <hi>Scotlands</hi> Method) and ſo reſtore the <hi>Biſhops;</hi> for that is it, they really intend,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116547:7"/>
though their words be ſmooth and faire as the greeneſt graſs, and garniſhed with <hi>His Majeſties own flowers, of preſerving the power and priviledge of Parliament, the juſt rights and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Subjects being reſtord, the eſtabliſhment of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Church-Government in purity, and the continuation of tho union of the two Kingdoms:</hi> (O admirable Hypocrites) <hi>according to the Covenant.</hi> (But here peepes the Snake) <hi>All Armies disbanded, and all your Souldiers juſt Accompts ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Kingdoms burthens caſed.</hi> What a turning and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this Snake keepes to hide himſelf <hi>King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Viper!</hi> ſo full of goodneſſe, ſo many ſeeming good deſires heapt together Appear boldly as at firſt. Men are but <hi>Adams,</hi> and Women <hi>Eves;</hi> thou needeſt not diſpair to deceive. But as that <hi>old Serpent</hi> thy Father, make account to deceive thy ſelfe moſt. Thy <hi>Head,</hi> thy <hi>Head</hi> proud <hi>Hydra-Monſter,</hi> by this thine own malicious policy, ſhall receive the foreſt bruiſe. And then (as at firſt) from the ſame <hi>ſeed of the wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> God, to thy torment (thou ſhalt ſee) will raiſe up a ſeed, even a Generation of men, that ſhall diſcover where thy <hi>Skalie Helme</hi> is penetrable and ſmite thee there, ſo that thou ſhalt ſtumble and fall, and never riſe again; but upon thy belly ſhalt thou creepe, and duſt ſhalt thou eat all the dayes of thy life: and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt lied and deſembled in this Petition and the like, in the name of the Lord, and haſt again lifted up thy hand againſt his deareſt and moſt precious Servants.</p>
            <p>O ye <hi>Men of the Common-Hall,</hi> flatter not your ſelves in theſe your miſchievous practices, but ſpeedily repent, for ſo ſure as God is in Heaven, he cannot ſuffer you to proſper in it. All the people will ſee, that moſt ungreatefully ye ſeeke <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> that you may have your wills without any regard at all to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> which but for you, would be quiet enough. This way which you take is a way that no conſiderate man can once immagine, will tend to peace; but that it is a meere trick and device to raiſe a <hi>new Warre</hi> againſt the <hi>Army, and all thoſe ye call Roundheads;</hi> it being impoſſible to do it by any other meanes, and which being done, what then will become of <hi>Trade?</hi> what then will become of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116547:8"/>
Peace? why, then the <hi>Scots</hi> muſt be called in, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> with other <hi>Forreigners.</hi> For what? To make Peace. Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Peace-makers to this poore Nation, they have prooved indeed. No, rather, call in <hi>Rupert</hi> and <hi>Maurice</hi> and they will do it, as ſoone and as effectually.</p>
            <p>It is incredible that <hi>Affliction, &amp; Impriſonment, and feare of death and</hi> imminent Warre, ſhould not make thoſe grave an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Gentlemen more apprehenſive of the danger they are already againe haſtily caſting them-ſelves, and the whole Kingdome into, that Men of <hi>Eſtats, Honour and Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> ſhould attempt things ſo hazardous, when as (no doubt) <hi>reaſon</hi> is to be had in wayes more ſafe. Doubtleſſe, if they would ſit down, and with greateſt deliberation, ſtudie a way to ruin the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Poſterity,</hi> to re-embroile this <hi>Nation</hi> in blood, to deſtroy themſelves and their part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers, certainly no course would be found like unto this. For what will not thoſe men doe, who have cordiallie op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the King in the late Warre, rather then ſuffer the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Malignants</hi> to bee their <hi>Maſters,</hi> as by a perſonall treaty is really intended.</p>
            <p>No matters could be in a fairer way towards an <hi>accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> then our differences lately were: They could not but have bin compoſed by this time, if men would have conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves to live as freinds one by another, and to have ceaſed to ſtrive for <hi>Masteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> good men there were and are, both in <hi>Parliament and Common-Councell,</hi> who made it their ſtudie, to have propoſed a ſafe and good condition to <hi>King Parliament Cittie and all ſorts of People.</hi> But this new hurrie and maddneſſ of a generall riſing, under the collour of a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall Treatie,</hi> hath put of their endeavours, till this heate be over, and mens experience of the miſerie of their owne evill waies, ſhould make them more apt to heare things reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſuch as really tend to the preſervation and juſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of all parties.</p>
            <p>Ceaſe therefore, as you love your ſelves, wives, Children, and Eſtats, as you love the Peace and ſettlement of your Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Countrie (too long turmoyled with an unnaturall warr)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116547:8"/>
ceaſe (I ſay,) and give over this under-hand raiſing of new forces, under colour of <hi>ſettling the Militia</hi> in all Counties and <hi>Cities,</hi> yee, as well as others will find it bitternes in the end. It will but increaſe your owne trouble, lengthen out the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of the People, conſume their waſted Eſtats, deſtroy their trades, which they will ſoone ſee, and Curſe and hate you for it. The <hi>Cry of the poore</hi> pei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ces the <hi>Heavens,</hi> the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a <hi>guilty Conſcience</hi> are inſupportable. Lay to Heart, I beſeech you, how drcadfull your condition will be, when you ſhall be ſo ſurrounded with Miſeries at once, a never dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Worme,</hi> gnawing your hearts within, and from without, the <hi>Vengeance</hi> both of God and Man, for your Hypocriſie, Treachery, and perfidiouſneſſe ready to over-whelm you.</p>
            <p>Ceaſe for ſhame, to depend any longer upon lyes and falſhoods wherein ye abound; God (ye ſee) hath already manifeſted his diſpleaſure againſt your bloody purpoſes, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up your greateſt hopes of ſucceſſe in <hi>Wales,</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> and now lately in <hi>Surrey,</hi> into the hands of thoſe, whom through pride and malice ye diſpiſe; your Dukes and Earles and great ones, (ſtriving againſt him) being no more then the meaneſt perſons.</p>
            <p>And this great heaſt of the Lords in runing ſo ſwiftly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons, and voting a perſonall Treaty, ſhewes but whoſe Lords they are, and whoſe work they do, and the miſchiefe intended thereby, will ſurely fall upon their own heads.</p>
            <p>They alſo but abuſe you and themſelves, in plotting to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band this Army by tricks and Court Arts; and tis ſtrange ye ſhould not think, that more belongs to it, then now after all Victories, to give up their Swords for a perſonall Treaty, yet ye are ſo tranſported with vane hope, as to believe ye have them upon a free lock: for ſay you a perſonall Treaty is vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the King muſt come, and being once out of that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Army, is reſolved not to treate, untill all forces in all parts be disbanded.</p>
            <p>If the Army then refuſe, O then ſay you, the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116547:9"/>
will inſtantly engage againſt<hi>:</hi> but ſtay a little, ſurely ye will be miſtaken, the whole Kingdom doubtleſſe will be wiſer and honeſter, then to expect ſuch folly and madneſſe in the Army, and will-be more carefull of their own quietneſſe, then to engage themſelves into a new Warre, upon ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and unconſcionable tearmes.</p>
            <p>If then ye will be happy, ſtudy things more equall and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Councels of wicked and treacherous men: for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye may flatter and deceive your ſelves, yet God is not a God that will be mocked, he that fitteth in Heaven laughes you to ſcorne, the Lord will have you in deriſion, and will daſh you in peeces, like a Potters Veſſell.</p>
            <closer>Ceaſe therefore, to do evill, learn to do well, ſeeke Peace and follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, leaſt if ye perſiſt in your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly courſes, he teare you in peeces, and there be none to help you.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
